1995年，宾州匹兹堡的警方正为两桩银行劫案挠头，案子多少有点蹊跷
In 1995, police in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania were investigating a pair of bank robberies that struck them as somewhat odd.
这两起劫案显然是团伙作案
The bank robberies were related
监控录像显示，作案的是同一拨人，手法也如出一辙
in that security footage had captured the same two men committing both in the same manner.
一人排队望风，另一人则掏出手枪直指出纳
One would wait in line, acting as a lookout, while the other stuck up the teller with a handgun.
两起案子下来，这伙人卷走了几千美刀
In both robberies, the men made off with a few thousand dollars.
这抢劫手法嘛，实在算不上高明
Not the most sophisticated of heists,
而且监控还把俩人拍得一清二楚
which paired with the fact the men were clearly recognizable in the footage,
他们似乎压根没想过要遮掩身份
and seemingly made no attempt to conceal their identities,
这让警方觉得，事情背后必有蹊跷
made it seem like there might be something more to this.
银行职员也确认，这俩人的脸看得真真儿的
The bank staff confirmed the men's faces were plainly visible.
没戴丝袜头套，没戴墨镜，也没贴假胡子
They weren't wearing tights, or sunglasses, or fake mustaches,
看上去也不像戴了假发或化了妆，啥掩饰都没有
and it didn't seem like they had wigs, or makeup, or anything like that.
这么简单粗暴的抢劫
For such straightforward robberies,
怎么着也得来个经典的巴拉克拉法帽加卫衣的标准套餐吧
you'd think they'd just have the classic balaclava and hood combo.
更诡异的是，这俩人似乎还特意冲着监控摄像头露出了微笑
Even stranger, the men had seemingly made a point of looking directly at the security cameras and smiling.
这到底演的是哪一出
What the hell was going on?
案发几天后
A few days after the robbery,
警方逮捕了克利夫顿·约翰逊
police arrested Clifton Johnson,
这家伙因去年的另外两起抢劫案正在被通缉
who was wanted in connection with two other robberies that had taken place the previous year.
警方很快意识到，约翰逊就是最近这起劫案里那个露着大脸望风的家伙
Police soon realized that Johnson was the plain-faced lookout in the recent bank robberies,
他自己也供认不讳
and he admitted it.
嘿，这可真是得来全不费工夫，看来他们还真是“素颜”抢银行啊
Huh. Well, that was easy. I guess they really did just rob a bank with no disguise.
那要抓到那个持枪的同伙，应该也不难吧
Shouldn't be too hard to find the gunman, then.
但几个月过去了，案子毫无进展
But several months passed with no further arrests,
警方最终只好把枪手的照片放到了本地新闻的《匹兹堡犯罪克星》节目上
and eventually the police released a photo of the gunman on Pittsburgh Crime Stoppers, a segment on the local news.
匿名举报蜂拥而至，节目播出不到一小时
Anonymous tips poured in, and within an hour of the broadcast,
警方就逮捕了麦克阿瑟·惠勒
police had arrested McArthur Wheeler,
他跟监控录像里的劫匪长得一模一样
who was a striking match with the robber on the surveillance footage,
而且名字也蠢得可以
and also had a stupid name.
麦克阿瑟一般作为姓使用
麦克阿瑟，当做名字
McArthur, as a first name.
Mc这个词根在盖尔语里是“儿子”的意思
The Mc part of these names is short for the Gaelic Mac,
就像罗纳德，唐纳德之子
which means son, as in Ronald, son of Donald.
所以麦克阿瑟根本就不算个正经名字
So McArthur doesn't even really have a name.
他只是“阿瑟之子”，我就纳闷他爹妈到底有谁叫阿瑟吗
He's just son of Arthur. I wonder were either of his parents even named Arthur?
闲话少说，当麦克阿瑟·惠勒看到自己持枪抢银行的清晰影像时
Anyways, when MacArthur Wheeler was shown images of what appeared to be a very clearly identifiable him
他整个人都懵了，脸上写满了困惑与绝望
robbing a bank with a gun, his response was one of confusion and despair.
他说
He said,
可是我涂了柠檬汁啊，我明明涂了柠檬汁
But I wore the lemon juice. I wore the lemon juice.
好吧，哥们，这家伙到底在说什么啊
Alright, well, what are you talking about?
惠勒解释说，是约翰逊说服他用一个天才计划去抢银行，保证能逍遥法外
Wheeler explained that Johnson had convinced him of a genius plan to rob the banks and get away with it.
约翰逊的妙计就是，柠檬汁
Johnson's idea was lemon juice.
你懂的，就是你小时候学到柠檬汁可以当隐形墨水
You know when you're a kid and you learn lemon juice can be used as invisible ink,
然后你就一辈子都记着这个冷知识
and then remember it for the rest of your life,
because when you're a kid you're certain that will one day prove invaluable information.
坚信这玩意儿有朝一日必成大器
显然，克利夫顿·约翰逊对这个知识点的记忆出了点偏差
Well, Clifton Johnson had obviously not remembered this very well,
他不知怎么就以为，既然柠檬汁能用来写密信
as he was somehow under the impression that just as lemon juice could be used to write hidden messages,
那它肯定也能在监控录像里“隐形”
it would also be undetectable in surveillance footage.
恕我直言，他大概是觉得，你根本没法给柠檬汁拍照，是这意思吧
Basically, he thought it was impossible to take a picture of lemon juice, I guess?
我猜他可能是摸到点门道了，意思是，你能在这张图里看见柠檬汁吗
I suppose he was sort of onto something. I mean, can you see any lemon juice in this picture?
不行吧
No,
但约翰逊不知怎地就认为，柠檬汁能把它涂抹的任何东西都遮盖掉
but Johnson somehow thought that the lemon juice would obscure whatever it was smeared on.
放在这个案子里，就是劫匪的脸
In this case, the bank robbers' faces.
惠勒告诉警方，他一开始也不信约翰逊
Wheeler told police he didn't initially believe Johnson.
麦克阿瑟，你看人真准
That's a good instinct, McArthur.
但他还是往自己脸上抹了点柠檬汁，然后用拍立得给自己拍了张照
But that was until he put some lemon juice on his face and then took a Polaroid picture of himself.
照片上，他还真消失了
He was absent from the photo.
这下他深信不疑，立马伙同约翰逊，顶着一脸柠檬汁去抢银行了
This convinced him to join Johnson in robbing banks with lemon juice smeared on his face.
警方也搞不明白，惠勒的实验是怎么“成功”的
Police could not account for how Wheeler's experiment was a success.
废话，最大的可能就是他瞎搞一气，根本没把自己拍进镜头里
Well, other than the likelihood that he had made up balls of it and just not been in frame.
也许是柠檬汁辣了眼睛，他压根没看清
Maybe he'd gotten lemon juice in his eyes and couldn't see right.
也许他就是个纯粹的啥比
Maybe he was just an idiot.
好吧，故事讲到这份上，他是不是啥比这事儿，已经毋庸置疑了
Well, I guess at this point in the story, his idiocy is beyond question.
法庭上，克利夫顿·约翰逊当庭指证了麦克阿瑟·惠勒，自己喜提五年监禁
In court, Clifton Johnson testified against McArthur Wheeler and received a five-year prison sentence.
惠勒则被判了24年
Wheeler went to prison for 24 years.
约翰逊这家伙听起来可真是个泌阳的
This Johnson guy sounds like a real jerk.
几年后，社会心理学家大卫·邓宁读到了这个柠檬汁劫匪的故事
A couple years later, David Dunning, a social psychologist, was reading about the story of the lemon juice robbers
他得出一个结论
and came to the conclusion,
如果说惠勒蠢到不配当个劫匪
if Wheeler was too stupid to be a bank robber,
蠢货！两个可以进博物馆的蠢货
那他可能也蠢到意识不到自己有多蠢
perhaps he was also too stupid to know that he was too stupid to be a bank robber.
也就是说，他的愚蠢，反而让他对自己的愚蠢浑然不觉
That is, his stupidity protected him from an awareness of his own stupidity.
1999年，他和他的研究生贾斯汀·克鲁格合著了一篇论文，标题是
With his graduate student, Justin Kruger, he authored a paper in 1999 entitled,
《既无能，且无知》
Unskilled and Unaware of It.
副标题是《论认知自身无能的困难，如何导致了过高的自我评估》
How difficulties in recognizing one's own incompetence lead to inflated self-assessments.
核心思想就是，当你无知时，你甚至都不知道自己有多无知
It's basically about how, when you're ignorant, you don't even know how much you don't know.
比如，如果我想做个游戏
Like, if I wanted to make a video game,
我对编程和3D建模略知一二，所以我知道这背后有太多我不懂的东西得学
I know enough about programming and 3D modeling to know that there are things I don't know and would have to learn.
比如动画绑定要刷权重，还有UV展开之类的
Like weight painting for the animation rig, or UV unwrapping.
因此，要说我能做个好游戏，我自己都没啥信心
Therefore, I would have pretty low confidence I could make a good video game.
但那些甚至不知道这些门道存在的人，大概会觉得这事儿比想象中简单多了
But someone who doesn't even know that stuff exists, probably thinks there's much less to learn than there actually is.
他们八成就是那种天天对开发者指点江山，说“你照某某做不就完了”的人
And is probably in the habit of telling game developers to just do X.
这类人总觉得，出点子才是最难的
The sort of person who thinks coming up with the ideas is the hard part.
水平有多低，信心就有多高
Minimal competence, maximum confidence.
这就是著名的“邓宁-克鲁格效应”，你以前可能听说过
This is known as the Dunning-Kruger effect, which you may have heard of before.
我觉得这故事最吓人的地方在于
I think the scariest part of this story
约翰逊和惠勒的行为，仅仅被归类为普通的人类愚蠢行为
is that Johnson and Wheeler's actions are just considered regular old human stupidity.
仿佛“柠檬汁能让摄像头发瞎”
Like, it's normal to think lemon juice makes things invisible to cameras,
或者“我是第一个想到这招的天才”这种想法，都很正常
or that you're the first person to think of this.
并且还对此迷之自信，甚至敢为此赌上后半辈子去抢银行
And to be so confident in this that you'd be willing to engage in such high stake risk as robbing a bank on the back of it.
对我来说，这太反常了，这已经不是典型的人类失误了
To me, that's abnormal. Like, that's not just typical human error.
这简直是严重的认知障碍
That's like, a serious impairment.
我只能理解为，这俩人要么是嗨大了
It only makes sense to me that these guys were massively drug-addled,
要么就是那种你真的不该嘲笑他们“愚蠢”的人
or they're the sort of people that you really shouldn't call stupid.
你懂的，这不好笑
You know, that's not funny.
关键是社会居然认为他们的智力在“可接受”范围内
The idea that they fall under an acceptable tolerance of intelligence,
允许他们无人监管地生活
that society allows them to live their lives unsupervised,
还能像我们其他人一样，被司法系统正常起诉
and be prosecuted by the justice system like any of the rest of us.
这事儿啊，在很多层面上都让人细思极恐
Now, that is concerning on many levels.
算了，对于用柠檬汁抢银行这种事，咱们还是别想太深了
Well, best not to think too deeply about bank robberies committed with lemon juice.
不如多看看我的其他视频
Instead, watch more of my videos.
风格类似，但主题各异
They're similar to this one, but cover different topics.
嘛，这话你大概也猜到了
Well, you probably could have guessed that.
关注我获取更多视频这一块
You can subscribe to see more of my videos in the future.
点了关注我更新你就能看见了
As in, you'll see the new ones as I make them.
或者你直接爆米进我的会员频道
And you can join the channel membership to support me monetarily.
就是说啥呢，你给我爆米支持我的创作
That means you give me money for my services to the community.
感谢收看，咱们下次再见，注意安全
Thank you, and until next time, stay safe.
1995年，警防……警芳……警坊……
In 1995, poliets in... poliets... poliets...
1995年，警芳……
In 1995, poliets... poliets...
你怎么一直说成警芳呢
Why do you keep saying poliets?
1995年，警芳……
In 1995, poliets...
案发几天后，警芳……
A few days after the robbery, poliets arefted...
感谢各位，下期再见，注意安全
1995年，警芳…警芳…警芳…
1995年，警芳…警芳…
你干嘛老说警芳啊
1995年，警芳…
案发几天后，警芳逮扑了…
逮扑…
啥
玩…
灯…
喔哇…
一个私密的喷嚏…
和…
玩…